This is דף ט, Daf Tet, we pick up on ח עמוד
ב Cheit Amud Bet at the top, so we have a little
catching up to do. And we have the גמרא Gemara sort of
transitioning to a discussion related to צדקה Tzedakah based on the whole
idea of, you know, obligating members of the community, so first it's
to provide of the town, provide for needs of the town, the
protection, water and so on, but then it sort of also brought
in making everybody participate in paying for the, you know, for the
care of the poor and the different types of care of the
poor and so on and we've already alluded to that before about
how long you have to be in a town until you, not
we alluded to, we directly mentioned the question, you know, if you're
living in there for a month, for six months, for a year,
you have to give to different types of the support of the
poor within the city. Okay, so within that context the גמרא Gemara
brings a story that the mother of שבור מלכא Shvor Malka sent
a wallet, a purse filled with דינרי Dinarei to רב יוסף Rav
Yosef and said use them for a מצוה רבה, Mitzvah Rabbah, and
he decided what is a מצוה רבה, Mitzvah Rabbah, מצוה רבה Mitzvah
Rabbah must be פדיון שבויים. Pidyon Shevuyim. Okay, and now we pick
up on the top of ח עמוד ב. Cheit Amud Bet.
Okay, the, okay so the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר ליה
רבא לרבה בר מרי, Amar Lei Rava L'Rabba Bar Mari, first line
of ח עמוד ב, Cheit Amud Bet, excuse me, מנא הא מילתא
דאמרי רבנן דפדיון שבויים מצוה רבה היא? Mina Ha Milta De'Amri Rabbanan
De'Pidyon Shevuyim Mitzvah Rabbah Hi? Where does this idea come from that,
you know, it's apparently well-accepted that this idea of פדיון שבויים Pidyon
Shevuyim is a מצוה רבה? Mitzvah Rabbah? Where does this come from?
אמר ליה דכתיב והיה כי יאמרו אליך אנה נצא ואמרת אליהם כה
אמר השם אשר למות למות ואשר לחרב לחרב ואשר לרעב לרעב ואשר
לשבי לשבי. Amar Lei De'Chasiv Ve'Haya Ki Yomru Elecha Ana Netzei Ve'Amarta
Aleihem Koh Amar Hashem Asher L'Maves L'Maves Va'Asher L'Cherev L'Cherev Va'Asher L'Raav
L'Raav Va'Asher L'Shevi L'Shevi.
Okay,
so whoever, you know, all these different deaths that are going to
befall people in the time of חורבן הבית, Churban Ha'Bayis, ואמר רב
יוחנן כל המאוחר בפסוק זה קשה מחבירו. Ve'Amar Rav Yochanan Kol Ha'Me'uchar
Be'Pasuk Zeh Kasheh Me'Chaveiro. So this פסוק Pasuk is going up in
degree of severity
of how a person
might die. Okay, so let's take a look, so חרב קשה ממות.
Cherev Kasheh Me'Maves. So death by the sword is worse than death,
presumably natural death. אי בעית אימא קרא ואי בעית אימא סברא. Ei
Bayis Eima Kra Ve'Ei Bayis Eima Sevara. Either you can learn this
from a פסוק Pasuk or you can just know it from your
own logic. אי בעית אימא סברא, Ei Bayis Eima Sevara, logically you
could derive this, האי קא מנוול והאי לא קא מנוול, Hai Ka
Menuval Ve'Hai Lo Ka Menuval, death by a sword causes the body
to become disfigured whereas natural death does not. ואי בעית אימא קרא,
Ve'Ei Bayis Eima Kra, and from a verse you see this. יקר
בעיני השם המותה לחסידיו. Yakar Be'Einei Hashem Ha'Mavesah La'Chasidav.
Dear to God is the death of His righteous, very interesting פסוק,
Pasuk, exactly what that means, but here it means the the dearest
type of death is natural death, not something like death by the
sword. Okay, so that's why it goes from אשר למות למות ואשר
לחרב לחרב, Asher L'Maves L'Maves Va'Asher L'Cherev L'Cherev, natural death first, death
by the sword next, and after death by the sword is רעב,
Raav, death by hunger. רעב קשה מחרב. Raav Kasheh Me'Cherev. אי בעית
אימא סברא, Ei Bayis Eima Sevara, you could learn it either from
logically, האי קא מצטער והאי לא קא מצטער. Hai Ka Mitztaer Ve'Hai
Lo Ka Mitztaer. Okay, death by the sword disfigures the body but
it's instantaneous. Death by hunger causes a great suffering along the way.
אי בעית אימא קרא, Ei Bayis Eima Kra, and you can learn
it by a verse. טובים היו חללי חרב מחללי רעב. Tovim Hayu
Chalalei Cherev Me'Chalalei Raav. There you go, it is an explicit פסוק.
Pasuk. Better were those that died by the sword than those that
died by hunger. שבי, Shevi, being taken captive, thank you, which is
the last thing in the פסוק, Pasuk, right, and that's פדיון שבויים,
Pidyon Shevuyim, right, שבי, Shevi, taken captive, קשה מכולם, Kasheh Mi'Kulam, is
more difficult than all of them, דכולהו איתנהו ביה, De'Chulhu Isnehu Bei,
you don't have to quote another פסוק, Pasuk, it just says you
have all of those things, you're, you know, you're in hunger and
you're fearful of death by the sword which is a possible end
result, so clearly, you know, and
you're, I guess I know we're supposed to sort of, we're behind,
but I just can't resist because to read this, let me see
if I can get a very quick the whole רמב"ם Rambam who
has a whole long, a little uncharacteristic of the רמב"ם Rambam about
how many מצוות Mitzvos are tied up in פדיון שבויים, Pidyon Shevuyim,
so give me just one quick second here.
What? Okay, you're kidding, you better be kidding. Okay, all right, so
hold on.
Okay, so you know what, I'm not finding it, so let's move
on.
Oh wait, let me just give one more second here. Yeah, פדיון
שבויים קודם לפרנסת עניים ולכסותן ואין לך מצוה,
Pidyon Shevuyim Kodem L'Parnasas
Aniyim U'Le'Chisusan Ve'Ein Lecha Mitzvah, פרק ח הלכה י Perek Cheit Halacha
Yud in מתנות עניים. Matnot Aniyim.
מצוה גדולה כפדיון שבויים שהשבוי הרי הוא
בכלל הרעבים והצמאים,
Mitzvah Gedolah Ke'Pidyon Shevuyim She'Ha'Shavui Harei Hu
Bi'Chlal Ha'Re'eivim Ve'Ha'Tzemei'im, the hungry, the the thirsty, והערומים, Ve'Ha'Arumim, the naked,
ועומד בסכנת נפשות, Ve'Omed Be'Sakanas Nefashos, which was which, you know, is
implicit in our גמרא Gemara because it's got all four forms of
death. והמעלים עיניו מפדיונו הרי זה עובר על לא תאמץ את לבבך
ולא תקפוץ את ידך Ve'Ha'Ma'alim Einav Mi'Pidyonu Harei Zeh Over Al Lo
Se'Ametz Es Levavcha Ve'Lo Sikpotz Es Yadecha and on.
They don't usually get this in a רמב"ם. Rambam. There's a very
strong rhetoric here. והצילו לקוחים למות v'hatzeilu lekuchim lamavet and many things
like this. ואין לך
מצווה רבה כפדיון שבויים. v'ein lecha mitzvah rabbah k'pidyon shevuyim. And it's
of course known how Jews would really, this would be a part
of Jewish history in the Middle Ages and beyond, people taken captive,
sometimes even by the government or others, and how the town, not
only the local towns, it would be even far away towns would
raise the money for פדיון שבויים. Pidyon Shevuyim. So clearly this has
always been something
of a high, very, very high priority.
They had side motives too.
Yes, and that was exactly sometimes the challenge. And that's why there's
a גמרא Gemara in גיטין Gittin about how do you sort of,
you know, once you start giving in and meeting their price and
then they just encourage it. So there's an interesting גמרא Gemara in
גיטין Gittin about balancing sort of, you know, policy issues and long-term
perspective against the immediate needs. מהר"ם Maharam of Rothenburg, his body, the
whole thing. Okay, so now we move on. Right.
Yes. Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Yeah, okay, absolutely. Absolutely. תנו רבנן.
Tanu Rabbanan. If you can't escape the contemporary relevance of every דף
daf we're doing these days. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. קופה של צדקה
נגבית בשנים ומתחלקת בשלושה. Kuppah shel tzedakah nigbeit bishnayim u'mit'chaleket bishloshah.
The box, you know, the collection plate of צדקה tzedakah is collected
by two people and divided by three. So you need sort of
two representatives, community representatives to collect it, appointed to collect it, and
three to divide it. נגבית בשנים שאין עושים שררות על הציבור פחות
משניים. nigbeit bishnayim she'ein osim srarot al hatzibur pachot mishnayim.
You do not take positions of authority over the ציבור tzibur by
yourself. You have to be shared. Cannot be division of powers, not
exactly. But anyway, it can't be all one person holds all the
power. So you need two people. And obviously this is power because
you compel people to give. It's not a free will thing, you
know, there's an element, obviously a lot of צדקה tzedakah is at
your own discretion, but there is a certain צדקה tzedakah that we've
been discussing that members of the town give and they're required to
give. And therefore if somebody comes to the house and demands it,
that's obviously a position of power and authority. ומתחלקת בשלושה, u'mit'chaleket bishloshah,
it's divided by three, כדיני ממונות k'dinei mamonot because it's like a
דיני ממונות dinei mamonot because you have to assess different people's needs
and how you're going to distribute it. Of course, the interesting question
is, there's also the דיני ממונות dinei mamonot when you collect. Different
people's ability to give, right? If it's not a flat type of
tax. So if you take a look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot
says מתחלקת בג' כדיני ממונות, mit'chaleket b'gimel k'dinei mamonot, ואם תאמר מהאי
טעמא נמי תהא נגבית בשלושה, v'im tomar me'hai ta'ama nami tehei nigbeit
bishloshah, ופירש רבינו תם לפי שהידוע סכום של כל אחד ואחד כמה
יתן. u'peresh Rabbeinu Tam lefi shehayadua s'chum shel kol echad v'echad kama
yitein.
So we're talking when either it's a flat tax or when it's
already established what each household has to give, then it's just about
the act of collecting. But if there really is an assessment done
of how much everybody has to give, that would also require three,
a type of a real serious weighing of how much each person
gives and how to distribute it. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
continues. תמחוי. Tamchui.
Now the תמחוי Tamchui is the soup kitchen. That was, they would
go around and everybody would give some soup each day, or not
soup, something of what they were cooking each day, and then it
would be distributed on a daily basis to the poor, whereas the
קופה kuppah was distributed more by money and on a weekly basis.
Okay, so תמחוי נגבית בשלושה ומתחלקת בשלושה. Tamchui nigbeit bishloshah u'mit'chaleket bishloshah.
You need three to collect it and three to distribute it. Why?
שגבויה וחלוקה שווים. she'gviyata v'chalukata shavim.
Because not because it somehow in principle needs more people, but since
you distribute it on the same day, it's a little crazy to
send two people to go collect it and then to find the
third person when it's time to distribute. Since you're sort of doing
it all sort of within sort of, it's a very quick turnover
there between the collecting and the distributing, you might as well have
the group together at the same time. תמחוי בכל יום, Tamchui be'chol
yom, and
the תמחוי Tamchui was distributed on a daily basis, the food. קופה
מערב שבת לערב שבת, Kuppah me'erev Shabbat l'erev Shabbat, and the קופה
kuppah which was money to provide for you for the week was
distributed on every Friday. תמחוי לעניי עולם קופה לעניי העיר. Tamchui l'aniyei
olam, kuppah l'aniyei ha'ir.
The תמחוי Tamchui was primarily designated for the poor of not particularly
of this town. You're just a passing through poor person, you need
a meal to eat, you go to the soup kitchen and you
get a meal to eat. If you live in the town, so
then the town provides for you, and it's also a little bit
more dignified, and they provide for you a week's, like they give
you money to support you for the week. Right? So you understand
why you don't necessarily want to give a week's worth of allowance
to somebody who's just passing through.
So that is primarily and that also makes more demands on the
people of the town to give the money that's going to be
used for that. So that is directed towards the poor of the
town and not the poor that are just passing through.
Okay, so now it says like this: רשאים בני העיר לעשות קופה
תמחוי ותמחוי קופה. rashaim bnei ha'ir la'asot kuppah tamchui v'tamchui kuppah.
And the people of the town can decide if they have leftover
money in one of those collections that they can switch it from
one to the other. Right? We have more money than we need
in the קופה, kuppah, let's put some of those funds into the
תמחוי Tamchui or vice versa. ולשנותה לכל מה שירצו. u'l'shanota l'chol mah
she'yirtzu. Not only can you go from one type of צדקה tzedakah
fund to the other, but for whatever they would like. of the
town regardless of how you categorize it. If you look at the
first line in תוספות, Tosafot, ולשנותה לכל מה שירצו, u'l'shonosa l'chol mah
she'yirtzu, נראה לרבינו תם nir'leh Rabbeinu Tam שיכולים לשנותה אף לדבר הרשות.
she'yecholim l'shonosa af l'devar ha'reshut. And even and if you look at
the end of that תוספות, Tosafot, three lines before the תוספות Tosafot
ends, וכן היה רבינו תם נוהג לתת מעות הקופה לשומרי
העיר, v'chein hayah Rabbeinu Tam noheg laseis ma'os hakuppah l'shomrei ha'ir, לפי
שעל דעת בני העיר נותנים אותם, l'fi she'al da'as b'nei ha'ir nosnim
osam, that they collected money for the קופה, kuppah, they didn't need
it for the עניים, aniyim,
and he would draw from those funds, or they he didn't want
maybe start a new collection fund, so he would just maybe on
a regular basis draw from the קופה kuppah funds to pay for
the people who would be guarding the town. Now you could try
to frame that as a מצוה mitzvah of course, you know, פיקוח
נפשות, pikuach nefashos, protecting people, but תוספות Tosafot said you didn't need
to frame it that way. Fundamentally it was כסף kesef collected by
the townspeople for the purpose for the purposes of the town identified.
So even though the specific one that was identified in the act
of collection was providing for the poor, whoever was in charge, and
that's of course always the question, who's in charge, okay, but whoever
was in charge, you know, or whichever body was in charge at
their discretion could decide to reassign it.
Why don't you say that they need three people to do that?
To decide how to reassign it? Yeah, so it's not maybe it
does, it's not saying at all who the body or who the
person is that makes that decision. You're right. So why isn't it?
That's like so missing from our גמרא Gemara is the question about
governance. I mean, you know, even the idea of
it does have it in the beginning because it said that you
need three to distribute.
Right, right, but right, but even that that's true, that's a degree
of government and of decision making and so on. Right. But the
bigger questions, you know,
תוספות Tosafot says that רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam seems to have done
it on his own.
Well, I assume he might have had a body with him but
they all listened to him anyway. So, but you're right. I mean,
that is missing from a lot of these discussions, right, is that
more sense of how do you make those collective, you know, or
decisions on behalf of the town and so on.
I guess the חברא chevra learning in רבינו תם's Rabbeinu Tam ישיבה
yeshiva didn't protect them.
No, didn't protect everybody else in the town.
This was clearly in the רב's Rav's discretion in his own.
Right, well we're going to get to the discretion. That's essentially, here
it is, the תקדים takdim to the idea of the discretionary fund.
We're going to keep on going. Okay, ולשנותה לכל מה שירצו, u'l'shonosa
l'chol mah she'yirtzu, back to the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. ורשאי בני עיר
להתנות על המדות ועל
השערים. v'rashai b'nei ir l'hasnos al ha'middos v'al ha'she'arim.
Now also and here again we get to the question of what
exactly is the body. It speaks about the townspeople as a as
a collective. The townspeople can make stipulations regarding the measures, like what
are the types of measures that are going to be used in
the town, which seems just like an arbitrary issue, but you know,
we always get in the גמרא Gemara different types of of, you
know, of measures in different places.
And the more important I think is the issue of על השערים,
al ha'she'arim, to set fixed prices, to say that you know, we
won't allow fish to be sold for more than five dollars a
pound, we won't allow, you know, bread to be sold for more
than one dollar a loaf, you know, fix some of the prices
in order to obviously it limits, you know, some of that free
capitalism but it makes provide, you know, protects people that need reasonable
prices for things, like even to this day in Israel, right, some
of the bread and milk is still, what do you call it,
subsidized and so on. That's subsidy, this is different, this is fixing
prices. Okay, and the word שעה. sha'ah. שער. sha'ar.
Yeah. Exactly, exactly.
Oh really, milk here subsidized? I didn't know that.
Oh, it has a fixed price.
Oh has a fixed price.
Oh I understand, a cap. That's what we're talking about. Right, right,
right. Right here, right, רש''י Rashi says right, רש''י Rashi says that
it's not fixed, it means capping it. Okay, ועל שכר פועלים, v'al
s'char poalim, and also about perhaps here's minimum wage, I'm not kidding,
right? It doesn't mean a maximum presumably that you pay the workers,
it means a minimum. ולהסיע על קיצתן. u'l'hasia al kitzatan. And this
word ולהסיע, l'hasia, the word קיצתן kitzatan means their like edicts and
ולהסיע l'hasia somehow means to fine, to fine regarding their edicts, meaning
to fine people who go against the rules that they have set.
Okay, and that's going to be very interesting we're going to get
to that. Their power to to implement fines for those that violate
the rules. And of course what's also missing from all of this
is what is the theoretical justification of all of this? Right, on
what basis exactly? But obviously this is the גמרא Gemara coming up
with the idea of a collective, you know, of a collective body
and making rules that govern the collective body, so it could be
maybe seen as a forerunner for an idea of corporation and so
on. Okay, so let's keep on going.
Okay. ולהסיע על קיצתן. u'l'hasia al kitzatan. אמר מר. amar mar. Now
we're going to unpack this. אין עושים שררות על הציבור פחות משנים.
ein osim s'raros al ha'tzibbor pachos m'shnayim. You cannot have people in
positions of authority only a single authority, you need at least two,
which is of course funny because מלך melech is one, but maybe
anybody who's not a מלך. melech. מנא הני מילי? m'na hanei milei?
אמר רב נחמן דאמר קרא amar Rav Nachman d'amar kra והם יקחו
את הזהב ואת התכלת ואת הארגמן, v'hem yikchu es ha'zahav v'es ha'techeles
v'es ha'argaman, they will take all of these things, which are again,
it's this very parallel case about collecting money to be given or,
you know, donations to be given to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
and it's multiple people that are that are being in the
in the position of of of, you know, of control here. Now
שררות, s'raros, שררות, s'raros, who is it? of honesty or trust. They
are trusted even individually, you know, the people you assign in these
positions to handle the funds correctly. Of course, it's a big question:
who do you assign in those positions? And even if you assign
somebody who's honest, you know, can people always resist temptation and so
on? But the גמרא Gemara is saying that our default relationship should
be to trust them. So it's really not a question of distrust.
מסייע ליה לרב חנינא דאמר רב חנינא: mesaye lay le'Rav Chanina d'amar
Rav Chanina: מעשה ומינה רבי שני אחים על הקופה. maaseh u'mina Rebbe
shenei achim al hakuppa.
רבי Rebbe assigned two brothers to supervise the קופה. kuppa. The point
being, as רש"י Rashi says, two brothers when it comes to matters
of trust count as one person. So from an issue of authority
and power, you can say, okay, we have two people, we've satisfied.
But if there was a real question of suspecting people and needing
somebody else to make sure that everybody is being honest, okay, then
two brothers are more naturally in collusion and it would not have
satisfied. So that shows that fundamentally there's not a concern here of
honesty. But again, it's so hard to say, you know, I can
say that as I guess an initial orientation, but it also seems
like it's almost asking for trouble if you, you know, apply that
blindly. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says like this: מאי שררותא? mai s'raruta?
דאמר רב... d'amar Rav... so where is that sense of power that
comes, you know, authority that comes through this position? I mean, you
just knock at the door and ask for some money. דאמר רב
נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה לפי שממשכנין על הצדקה ואפילו בערב שבת.
d'amar Rav Nachman amar Rabba bar Avuha lefi shememashkenin al hatzedaka v'afilu
b'erev Shabbos. Because if somebody doesn't want to give the funds that
they're required to give, you can take collateral from their house. Like
goes back to בבא מציעא Bava Metzia issues, entering their house and
take collateral. So you actually are exerting your power over them. איני,
eini, is that really true? והכתיב ופקדתי על כל לוחציו? v'haksiv u'fakadeti
al kol lochatzav? I, God, will punish all those who oppress them.
דאמר רבי יצחק בר שמואל בר מרתא משמיה דרב ואפילו גבאי צדקה.
d'amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar Shmuel bar Marta mishmei de'Rav v'afilu gabai tzedaka.
This refers even to the גבאי צדקה gabai tzedaka collectors that oppress
the people, you know, use their power against the people to collect
the money. So here, you know, clearly you're not supposed to be
using your power. לא קשיא הא דאמיד הא דלא אמיד. lo kashya
ha d'amid ha d'lo amid.
The question is whether the person who you're using your power against
actually has means or doesn't have means. With the poor person, then
you should not be exerting your power. If it's a person who's
wealthy and still doesn't want to be giving, then you go ahead
and you take collateral and you force them to pay. כי הא
דרבא אכפיה לרב נתן בר אמי ושקל מיניה ארבע מאה זוזי לצדקה.
ki ha de'Rava achpei le'Rav Natan bar Ami u'shakal minei arba mea
zuzei l'tzedaka. Okay, רבא Rava forced רב נתן בר אמי—it's Rav Natan
bar Ami interesting, right? An אמורא, amora, fellow אמורא amora was resisting—maybe
because as we see, a lot was being demanded from him, four
hundred זוז, zuz, right? Which presumably we're dealing with a progressive tax
here, you know, and he used his power to force him to
pay because he had the means even though he didn't want to
give. Okay, there's a very famous תוספות, Tosafos, I know, I'm trying
to we're catch up but I can't resist some of this. I'll
just read the first line of תוספות: Tosafos: אכפיה לרב נתן. achpei
le'Rav Natan. תוספות Tosafos asks a classic question which תוספות Tosafos frames,
frames: ואם תאמר ובפרק כל הבשר אמר כל מצות עשה שמתן שכרה
כתובה בצדה אין בית דין של מטה מוזהרין עליה. v'im toma u've'perek
kol habasar amar kol mitzvas asei shematan sechara kesuva betzidah ein beis
din shel mata muzharin aleha. Any positive מצוה mitzvah where the תורה
Torah speaks explicitly identifies the reward you'll get, בית דין, Beis Din,
the way תוספות Tosafos is reading it, does not have the power,
does not have the authorization to use power to enforce it. And
צדקה, tzedaka, it tells you, right? It says כי בגלל הדבר הזה
יברכך השם
אלקיך. ki biglal hadavar hazeh yevarekcha Hashem elokecha. Since the reward is
written right there in the פסוק, pasuk, תוספות Tosafos says why how
does בית דין Beis Din have the power to enforce, you know,
that? And what it raises is the point that צדקה tzedaka is
two things, of course. It's a מצוה. mitzvah. So if the תורה
Torah says if you honor your parents, you'll get long life, and
you're not honoring your parents, I, the בית דין, Beis Din, can't
beat you up to make you honor your parents. Okay, if it
says, you know, so let if you send away the mother bird
you'll get long life and you're not doing it, I can't force
you to do it. I can force you, this is based on
the idea that בית דין Beis Din can force somebody to put
on תפילין, tefillin, to sit in a סוכה, sukkah, they can actually
use physical force to get people to do מצוות. mitzvos. So much
for no כפיה דתית, kfiah datis, okay, in the גמרא. Gemara. But
I can't force you to do a מצוה mitzvah that the תורה's
Torah already promised what its reward is. Then, you know, that maybe
should be enough of an incentive. The point with צדקה tzedaka is
that it's not just a מצוה, mitzvah, right? It's providing for the
poor. There's like a דיני ממונות dinei mammonos element to צדקה. tzedaka.
So we it's interesting to distinguish. I can't get you to put
on, you know, to be send away the mother bird, but I'm
not doing it here because I care about your מצוה. mitzvah. I'm
doing it here because I care about the poor that needs to
be provided. So תוספות—you'll Tosafos see if you want you can look
at תוספות—he Tosafos gives different answers, but it raises this interesting question
of when does בית דין Beis Din use their power and when
are they authorized to use their power or not.
כפיה kfiah is one of
his answers, in other words... Yeah, yeah, exactly. Levels of כפיה, kfiah,
different types of things, exactly. Okay, back to גמרא. Gemara. והמשכילים
יזהירו כזוהר הרקיע. vehamaskilim yazhiru kezohar harakia. The משכילים, maskilim, oh look
at this, our modern contemporary, you know, the what do they call,
the השכלה, Haskalah, right, you know, the Enlightenment, whatever... Anyway, no, that's
where they got their name from. Anyway,
you know, those that are, what's a good translation of משכילים? maskilim?
Those that understand, you know, the under... will shine like the shining
of the sky. So what does that mean? What's that refer to?
זה דיין שדן דין אמת לאמיתו. Ze dayan shedan din emet l'amito.
This is a judge that judges a true, you know, the depths
of the true justice. What תוספות Tosafot says, why do you need
to say דין אמת לאמיתו? din emet l'amito? Just say דין אמת.
din emet. So תוספות Tosafot says no, because you can follow the
rules and it will not be a דין אמת din emet because
you're not really looking below the surface. Like somebody comes and presents
evidence and if you really looked into it, you'd realize something is
smelly here, something fishy here. So by just following the rules you're
not being דן דין אמת לאמיתו. dan din emet l'amito. That's why
you have to be a משכיל. maskil. You know, you have to
be smart. You have to be able to read between the lines,
you have to be able to see what's really going on. So
if you're that's the דיין dayan that's דן דין אמת לאמיתו. dan
din emet l'amito. Okay. ומצדיקי הרבים, Umatzdikei harabim, the reason we're quoting
it is because of the end of the
פסוק. pasuk. ומצדיקי הרבים ככוכבים לעולם ועד. Umatzdikei harabim kekhochavim le'olam va'ed.
Those that, you know, do righteousness towards the, or defend maybe, you
know, the masses. But we're reading it from the word of צדקה,
tzedakah, provide צדקה tzedakah for the masses,
will be like the stars for ever and ever. Okay,
so אלו, eilu, okay, mine has a י. yud. אלו גבאי צדקה.
Eilu gabbei tzedakah. So the מצדיקי matzdikei is read as those that
collect the צדקה. tzedakah. Okay, so it's all, and it's also, it's
a little interesting play of the מצדיקי matzdikei
because להצדיק, lehatzdik, right, is he feels the cause. So it means
to cause others to give צדקה tzedakah for the masses. Okay, or
causing the masses to give צדקה. tzedakah. So we're not just talking
about those that give it, but those that actually make it happen.
The מצדיקי הרבים matzdikei harabim are the גבאי צדקה. gabbai tzedakah. They
will shine forever and ever. ובמתניתא תנא, Uv’masnisa tana, in a ברייתא
Baraisa we taught, והמשכילים יזהרו כזהר הרקיע, Vehamaskilim yazhiru kezohar harakiya, זה
דיין שדן דין אמת לאמיתו. Ze dayan shedan din emet l'amito. That's
we said already, the judge who gets to the depths of the
justice. וגבאי צדקה, Vegabbai tzedakah, and it includes the גבאי צדקה. gabbai
tzedakah. That's included in משכילים. maskilim. Why are they משכילים? maskilim? Because
you have to know how to collect from each person, how to
distribute the funds, things we talked about before. So what's ומצדיקי הרבים
ככוכבים לעולם ועד? umatzdikei harabim kekhochavim le'olam va'ed? אלו מלמדי תינוקות. Eilu
melamdei tinokos. Those are the people that teach the young kids. Okay,
they are מצדיקי הרבים matzdikei harabim because you know, as it said,
the future of any people has always been the next generation, right?
You teach the next generation and there you are really doing, you
know, that's the best contribution you can make for the whole community.
It says Midrash on education.
Yeah, what does he say?
No, he says that you create a lot of pupils like shining
stars. It's very nice.
Oh really? Yeah, very nice. Okay, very nice. I'll have to look
at it, I did not look at it. Okay. כגון מאן? Kegon
man? Now, who would be a good example of מצדיקי הרבים matzdikei
harabim that really, you know, had self-sacrifice for teaching his pupils? אמר
רב כגון רב שמואל בר שילת. Amar Rav kegon Rav Shmuel bar
Shilas. The example of
רב שמואל בר שילת. Rav Shmuel bar Shilas. How, what's the example?
דרב אשכחיה לרב שמואל בר שילת דהוה קאי בגינתא. Derav ashkechei le-Rav
Shmuel bar Shilas de-hava ka'ei be-ginsta. One day Rav found Rav Shmuel
bar Shilas that he was actually walking in his garden taking a
five-minute break. אמר ליה שבקתיה להימנותך? Amar lei shavaktia le-heimanusach? Have you
abandoned your post? Have you abandoned, have you abandoned, you know, you've
been entrusted with these kids. You're on a break? אמר ליה
הא תליסר שנין דלא חזיא לי. Amar lei ha tlisar shanin dela
chazya li. For 13 years I have never, I haven't seen my
garden. Okay, this is the first time in 13 years that I've
walked into my garden. והשתא נמי דעתאי עילוייהו. Vehashta nami da’atai ilvayeihu.
And even now while I'm here, I'm still thinking about the kids
and about that I left behind, that I have to get back
to the classroom. All right, so Rabbi Dov, you'll have to use
this one when you're in your educators class.
It's like micromanaging principals. Okay. רבנן מאי? Rabbanan mai? Now, all of
that is for the דיין dayan and for the גבאי צדקה gabbai
tzedakah and for those that teach the small school children. How about
the rabbis?
So רבנן מאי? Rabbanan mai? אמר רבינא ואוהביו כצאת השמש בגבורתו. Amar
Ravina ve’ohavav ketzes hashemesh bigvuraso. That's even greater. That, those that love
God, that demonstrate the love because of constantly learning תורה, Torah, they'll
be as strong as when the sun comes out, not the sky,
not the stars, but as this rising sun. תנו רבנן גבאי צדקה,
Tanu rabbanan gabbai tzedakah, back to צדקה. tzedakah. גבאי צדקה אינן רשאין
לפרוש זה מזה. Gabbai tzedakah einan rasha'in lifrosh ze mize. Here we
are, we are going and collecting, we're these two people and we're
going together because of שררה serarah requires two people. And you know,
we come to a certain section of the city. I can't say,
you go to that house, I'll go to the other house. Because
then when we're going to the individual houses, we're not operating as
two, we're operating as one.
אינן
רשאין לפרוש זה מזה. Einan rasha'in lifrosh ze mize.
אבל פירש זה לשער וזה לחנות. aval peirash ze l'sha'ar veze l'chanus.
One guy can go to the gate and to collect I guess
from the guy standing in the gate and the other guy to
the store because רש״י Rashi says they're presumably they're both open and
you can see one another. So if you're in sight of one
another, that still counts. Okay. מצא מעות בשוק. Matza ma’os bashuk. Now,
we mentioned before that fundamentally you are, you know, you trust them.
You don't... respect them. And so but and now they have to
act in a way that lives up to that trust, not obviously
just being honest, but also acting in ways that puts them above
suspicion. Okay, so that now we're going to explain how that plays
out. מצאו matza'o בשוק bashuk לא lo יתן yiten לתוך l'toch כיסו.
kiso. Let's say you're walking and you're doing your job and somebody
$20 bill on the ground, it's an אבדה. aveida. You can halakhically
you can pick it up and keep it for yourself, but don't
put it in your pocket right now, because somebody sees you taking
$20 and they only see you with the $20 bill that went
into your pocket and you're a גבאי צדקה, gabbai tzedaka, they're going
to think, you know, that you basically are pocketing צדקה tzedaka money.
So what do you do? So אלא ela נותנים notnim לתוך l'toch
ארנקי arnaki של shel צדקה, tzedaka, put that 20 bucks into the
pouch that you're carrying, you know, that's the for צדקה tzedaka funds
that you're collecting. וכשיבוא u-che-she-yavo לביתו l'veito יטלם. yitlem. And then when
you get home, then you can take your $20 back out of
it. Okay, so you know, because somebody's looking into your house and
sees you take the money out of the pouch of צדקה, tzedaka,
maybe
then they take you out.
Could be. All right, that's a good point. Okay, כיוצא k'yotzei בו
bo שמלו shamlo היה hayah לו lo בחבירו b'chavero מנה. maneh. Now,
here I am, I'm a גבאי צדקה, gabbai tzedaka, and David here
has owed me $100 for a while. Okay, ופרעו u-paro בשוק. bashuk.
And David comes up to me and says, "Aytov, I've been waiting
to find you, here's my $100 that I owe you." He gives
me $100, what do I do with it? Put it in my
pocket? What if somebody thinks David gave me money and I put
it in my pocket and I'm a גבאי צדקה? gabbai tzedaka? So
what do I do? So
לא lo יתננו yitneno לתוך l'toch כיסו. kiso. Don't put it in
your pocket. אלא ela נתנו notnu לתוך l'toch ארנקי arnaki של shel
צדקה, tzedaka, put it into the צדקה tzedaka pouch, וכשיבוא u-che-she-yavo לביתו
l'veito יטלם, yitlem, and when you come to your home, then you
can take the money out. Wow, it's basically מראית עין. marit ayin.
But it's a מראית עין marit ayin not about ritual matters but
about being above suspicion in monetary dealings, especially when you're in a
position of trust. Okay, תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, Rabbis taught: גבאי צדקה
gabbai tzedakah. שאין she'ein להם lahem עניים ani'im לחלק. l'chalek. Let's say
we collected all this money
and we don't have any עניים ani'im this week, you know, and
so we want obviously to protect the money we collected, but we
collected it in all of these copper coins which will rust, and
therefore we'd like to switch it for silver coins which will last
longer. Okay, don't you be the one to switch with your own
money. Okay, עניים ani'im לחלק l'chalek פורטין portin לאחרים. l'acherim. You do
a swap of the copper with the silver coins with other people,
ואין ve-ein פורטין portin לעצמן. l'atzman. Not yourself, because somebody will see
you took all these coins, you put back silver, like, okay, maybe
he took a percentage off for himself in the process, right? So
again, you have to operate above suspicion. גבאי gabbai תמחוי, tamchui, similarly,
those that collected the food, שאין she'ein להם lahem עניים ani'im לחלק,
l'chalek, and now you have no עניים ani'im to distribute and really
the food is going to go bad. מוכרין mochrin לאחרים, l'acherim, you
have to sell the food to other people, ואין ve-ein מוכרין mochrin
לעצמן. l'atzman. Don't sell to yourself. It doesn't matter if you're even
going to be generous in how much you're going to pay for
it, that's not what it looks like, or that's not what it
might look like. Okay. מעות ma'ot של shel צדקה tzedaka אין ein
מונין monim אותם otam שתים shtayim שתים shtayim אלא ela אחת achat
אחת. achat. When you have the צדקה tzedaka money, you do not
count them, like, you know, two at a time, like, you know,
$2 at a time, okay, because you count them as, you know,
one at a time, one, two, three, you count the cash. Now
רש״י Rashi says this is also an issue about suspicion. רש״י Rashi
says פן pen יאמרו yomu שתים shtayim הוא hu נוטל notel ואינו
ve-eino מונה mone אלא ela אחת. achat. If somebody sees you counting
them two at a time, they're going to say that when you
were counting them, you were counting one, two, three, not two, four,
six, and you are sort of keeping some behind for yourself. So
it has to be everything done very clear. Okay, skimming off the
top. Okay, אמר amar אביי Abaye מריש meresh לא lo הוה hava
יתיב yasiv מר mar אציפי atzipi דבי d'vei כנישתא. knishta. Originally the
master, Rabba, used to not sit by the mats that were in
use that were placed in the שול, shul, you know, they didn't
have chairs they had mats. Why? כיון kevan דשמע d'shama להא l'ha
דתניא d'tanya ולשנותו v'lishnoto לכל l'chol מה mah שירצה, she-yirtze, because but
then when he heard the הלכה halakha that the people when you
collect צדקה tzedaka funds you can reassign them however you see fit
for the town's people can reassign them or whoever's in the position
of overseeing it, הוה hava יתיב yasiv he would sit. Because apparently
those mats were bought with leftover צדקה tzedaka funds. So he felt,
I can't sit on it, you know, they were made for the
שול, shul, it was a מצוה, mitzvah, but he felt I can't
sit on it, it should be given to עניים. ani'im. And then
he said, oh, no, actually you do have the right to reassign
צדקה tzedaka funds even to non-עניים ani'im purposes. Okay, now the
גמרא Gemara says הוה hava יתיב yasiv he would sit. אמר amar
אביי Abaye מריש meresh הוה hava עביד avid מר mar תרי trei
כיסי. kise. Now usually the master, Rabba, would make two separate pouches.
חד chad לעניי l'ani'ei דעלמא d'alma וחד v'chad לעניי l'ani'ei דמתא. d'masa.
And he when he would collect money, he would put money for
the, you know, for the general poor into one pouch and the
money he collected for the poor of the town into another pouch.
כיון kevan דשמע d'shama להא l'ha דאמר d'amar להו l'hu שמואל Shmuel
לרב l'Rav תחליפא Tachlifa בר bar אבדימי, Avdimi, once he heard what
Shmuel said to
רב l'Rav תחליפא: Tachlifa: עביד avid חד chad כיסא kisa ואתני עלה.
ve-atni alah. Look, you can just have one
pouch and you could just stipulate, I'm collecting fund, I'm putting it
all in one pouch, and I'll decide later how to distribute. Right,
that obviously is an outcome of the idea that you can switch
the assignment. But maybe here part of the חידוש chiddush is that
you can even לכתחילה lechatchila sort of mix them up since in
the end I'm going to have the discretion, even לכתחילה lechatchila I
can mix it up. And you do understand a bit of a
חידוש chiddush because there's a little bit more of an inertia and
a resistance, like, if you if you put them. something in one
account and another, you have to say, wait, wait, wait, is it
justified to move it out of this account to some other purpose?
If you just throw everything in the same account to begin with,
you know, you could understand that that's not the same idea. Nevertheless,
he said it was allowed. One minute, to put, you know, to
you collect for different purposes, but you put it all in the
same pouch. Okay, אי נמי עביד חד קצא ואתני, Iy nami avid
chad katzah ve-atni, he also makes just one pouch and he just
stipulates that he'll decide how to distribute it. ואתני v'asni עלה. aleh.
רב אשי Rav Ashi אמר אנא אתנויי נמי לא צריכנא. amar ana
itnuyei nami lo tzerichna. I don't even have to explicitly stipulate. דכל
דקא אתי אדעתה דידי אתי. de-chol de-ka atei ada'atah didi atei. Anybody
who gives money to צדקה tzedaka and gives it to me as
a צדקה tzedakah collector knows that I have my discretion and accepts
my discretion about how to distribute it. Okay, but it's a little
funny because if I go to David and say, David, we're doing
the collection for the עניי העיר, aniyei ha-ir, right? He at least
expects that the default will be עניי העיר aniyei ha-ir unless there's
a reason that I need to switch it. So you sort of
understand if initially it's announced just give it to my discretionary fund
as opposed to if initially it's identified and then you don't and
then לכתחילה lechatchila you just throw it all into the same
into the same account. Yes, Jenna.
אביי? Abaye? אביי Abaye is Mara's רבה. Rabba.
So why, I don't know, is that normal for like great רבנים
Rabbis to be צדקה tzedakah collectors?
It seems like it, yeah. I mean, well, yeah. I mean because
well, it's sort of like, you know, you give now to the
רב rabbi's discretionary fund. Meaning, whether they were the ones to knock
on the door, right, or whether they were sort of, you know,
the in charge as it were and they had people to help
them do the day-to-day like that's an interesting collection. But certainly that
they were sort of the ones that were had the discretion here,
took the responsibility of the position. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. Okay, אדעתה דידי אתי ולמאן דניחא לי יהבנא ליה.
ada'atah didi atei u-le-man de-nicha lei yehavna leh. Okay, I didn't finish
the sentence. And I'll give it to whom I see fit. Okay,
הנהו בי תרי טבחי. hanhu bei terei tavchei. Now we're going to
switch a little bit from צדקה tzedakah to the next part of
that ברייתא braita because the end of that ברייתא braita spoke about
being able to, you know, stipulate, make rules for the city about
what the capping income, you know, minimum wage, capping prices. And then
it says and to punish people who violate those rules. So that's
sort of what we're shifting to now, although we haven't signaled it.
הנהו בי תרי טבחי דעבדי עניינא בהדי הדדי. hanhu bei terei tavchei
de-avdi inyana bahadi hadadei. There were two shepherds, there were two butchers,
thank you, who had a deal between them. Like they sort of,
you know, they had a, what are those called, a guild as
it were. Okay,
you know, they made an arrangement between them. דכל מאן דעביד ביומא
דחבריה ניקרעוהו למשכיה. de-chol man de-avid be-yoma de-chavreih nikreuhi le-mashcheih. Anybody that
they sort of alternated days, you know, works good if you have
a שבת Shabbos so two people so every, you know, whatever, you
divide the week, Monday, Wednesday, what is it, Monday, Wednesday, Friday, whatever,
anyway. Okay, anyway, I can't Monday, Wednesday, Friday, right, Sunday, Tuesday, Thursday.
Anyway, they divided the week and they said if you work on
my day then if anybody works on the other person's day then
they're going to be fined. How are they going to be fined?
We're going to take the skin from your animal and we're going
to just tear it up into shreds, which obviously would be a
big financial loss. Okay, I still want to have the one to
work on Friday because I think you'll get, anyway. אזל חד מנייהו
עבד ביומא דחבריה. azal chad mineihu avad be-yoma de-chavreih. One of them
went, he worked on his friend's day. קרעו למשכיה. karei le-mashcheih. They
tore up his the animal hide. אתו לקמיה דרבא. atu le-kameih de-Rava.
Came to רבא. Rava. חייבינהו רבא לשלומי. chayavinhu Rava le-shlumei. רבא Rava
said the guy who tore up the hide has to pay. Why,
what gave him that right? איתיביה רב יימר בר שלמיא לרבא. eitiveih
Rav Yeimar bar Shelameya le-Rava. So רב יימר בר שלמיא Rav Yeimar
bar Shelameya challenged רבא. Rava. We taught in the ברייתא, braita, ולקיצותן.
u-le-ktzotan. You can fine people who violate the rules and they made
a rule here as a group. So the גמרא Gemara says, לא
אהדר ליה רבא. lo ahadar leh Rava. רבא Rava ignored him. אמר
רב פפא שפיר עבד דלא אהדר ליה. amar Rav Papa shapir avad
de-lo ahadar leh. רב פפא Rav Papa said רבא Rava did well
to ignore him. Why? דלא אהדר ליה מידי. de-lo ahadar leh midi.
That he didn't respond anything. הני מילי היכא דליכא אדם חשוב. hanei
milei heicha de-leika adam chashuv. When is it that you can make
rules like this with consequences? If there's not an important person around
in the town. אבל היכא דאיכא אדם חשוב לאו כל כמינייהו דמתנו.
aval heicha de-ika adam chashuv lav kol kemineihu de-matnu. But if there's
an important person in the town, you can't just make this rule,
you have to get the okay of the important person. Now, what
the heck is this about? What does the role of an important
person, meaning somebody like רבא, Rava, presumably a religious authority, in some
arrangement of butchers? Okay, so first of all, the ר"י מיגאש Ri
Migash says and it's quoted by the lot of the ראשונים Rishonim
that אדם חשוב adam chashuv here means two things and you require
both of them. Number one, it means a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham
and number two it means somebody who is in a position of
actual like a leadership political position of the town. She said if
you have one without the other, that's not called an אדם חשוב.
adam chashuv. And if you don't have an אדם חשוב adam chashuv
it's good, you can make your arrangements without anybody's authority. But if
the town has somebody who is a leadership position like, you know,
sort of a political leadership position and is also a significant תלמיד
חכם, talmid chacham, you need him to okay the decisions. Now, why
do you need him to okay the decisions? What does that's the
ר"י מיגאש. Ri Migash. Okay, why do you need him to okay
the decisions? So here the רמב"ן Ramban makes a very nice point.
I don't know if all the other ראשונים Rishonim agree, but the
רמב"ן Ramban says because the... A decision like this of alternating days
is not just a decision between the butchers. It has a huge
impact on the people of the town. It means that there's going
to be less competition. It means that the prices are going to
be higher. Okay, so therefore, the decision that you're going to make
is going to impact the, have policy implications. So you can't just
do it amongst yourselves, like you're שותפים shutfim and you're just making
some internal rules. When it impacts the town, you need the okay
of somebody who's in a leadership position. Now, the point of saying
that you have to be both means obviously you want to bring
both that sense of responsibility and knowledge about the realities of the
town and a תורה Torah הלכה halachic perspective to that decision process.
So that would be the bringing of those two together. But I
think there's a very nice idea that he says it's specifically because
this impacts other people in the town. It's not just between you,
רמב"ן. Ramban. Okay, so anyway, so now this by the way, the
other interesting issue that comes up here, not in our גמרא Gemara
but in the ראשונים rishonim that discuss this, is could you have
similar rules amongst in a business venture? We're going in a business
venture, we're all investing this money, here are the rules, here are
the consequences for violating, etc., etc. So basically the ראשונים rishonim say
no. This is only something that is recognized as a collective that
you can make these rules. Remember, it started in the ברייתא Baraita
about townspeople. The actual חידוש chidush that occurred here that you might
not have noticed this shift was a shift between seeing the town
as a collective that can have its own governance and make its
own rules with consequences and going to a sense of essentially a
guild, a sense of all of the butchers of the town. And
the ראשונים rishonim say if it was just a few butchers, they
can't make these rules. They're just individual people trying to make these,
there's no mechanism for making these rules. It has to be something
that is recognized as a type of a corporate entity. So if
you have all the butchers of the town, that's essentially like a
guild. I don't know if there were guilds in the time of
the גמרא Gemara or if the ראשונים rishonim were retrojecting it. But
anyway, but they said if it's something like a town or a
guild, a collective that includes all those members of a particular class
or profession, then they are somewhat of a corporate entity and can
make these types of rules with the consequences. But if you just
had two butchers making it or two people going into some business
venture, they would not have the same sort of latitude and they
would not have the same power.
And that's why you need an אדם חשוב adam chashuv as it
were.
Well, the אדם חשוב adam chashuv is like a different point.
Not a guild, it's just a couple of guys.
No, no, no, the אדם חשוב adam chashuv is in addition. But
I say this whole thing only starts to have the conversation if
you're dealing with a guild, that these butchers were not just two
butchers out of ten, they had to be all the butchers in
the town. And only then do you start having the power to
implement these rules with consequences and so on. Otherwise, you have to
work through normal rules of contracts and other types of things. These
powers here, who gives powers to make rules with consequences? That is
because it's seen of as a sort of collective, as a governance
of a collective. So you have to define what constitutes a collective
that can have a sense of governance with and pass its own
rules and have consequences on its rules. So that's what the ראשונים
rishonim say that the shift here is from town to everybody in
a particular profession, but that it would not
apply unless you make contracts that would work. But fundamentally this basic
power would not apply to just some random individuals or some subset
of people in a profession.
So is the guild doing a monopoly price fixing or are they
a...
Well, that's a good question. That's a good question. Right, because the
townspeople can also make rules that presumably would override the rules of
the guild, right? The townspeople could say, you know, you can't fix
the prices, you can't do this. And that's part of exactly what
the אדם חשוב adam chashuv is. That's right, is that to balance
the sort of interests of the guild with the interests of the
rest of the town. That's exactly what the רמב"ן Ramban says. Okay,
so it's exactly that. Yes. Just go.
And in the when we talked about שררה, serarah, we talked about
the
power of the butchers or like, so then you need somebody higher
to balance that.
Yeah, that's exactly what, exactly, that's exactly what the אדם חשוב adam
chashuv here is. Right, right, right, that's exactly that. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Of course even here the question
is, is it only by consensus? Let's say there's one guy vetoing
the decision, right? Other issues of governance and decision making are sort
of are not spelled out here. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
continues like this. Like this stuff is just too good. Anyway, okay,
it says like this. היכא דאיכא אדם חשוב לאו כל כמינייהו דמתנו.
heicha de'ika adam chashuv lav kol k'minaihu dematnu. Fine. תנו רבנן. tanu
rabanan. A ברייתא. Baraita. אין מחשבין בצדקה עם גבאי צדקה. ein m'chashvin
bitzedakah im gabai tzedakah. Back to צדקה. tzedakah אין מחשבין בצדקה עם
גבאי צדקה. ein m'chashvin bitzedakah im gabai tzedakah.
So this goes back to this issue of trust and again, I
don't know, to me this sounds like it's asking for trouble. I
mean, this really I guess forces you to make sure the person
you are appointing is really totally beyond beyond reproach. But a
person of repute, I should say. This is what's-his-face, beyond something. Anyway,
is a person of very high repute beyond any suspicion because it
says you do not actually check the accounts of the גבאי צדקה.
Gabbei Tzedakah. גבאי צדקה. Gabbei Tzedakah Once you appoint them you have
to trust them and you cannot come at the end of the
month or the week or the year and say, "Let me see
your books, let me see the money you collected, let me see
how you distributed it," you know, this is like unfortunately our experience
has shown that this is really asking for trouble, these people it's
a very high temptation, but this is what the גמרא Gemara says.
אין מחשבין בצדקה, Ein mechasvin bitzdakah, you do not go ahead and
check the books of the גבאי צדקה Gabbei Tzedakah עם גבאי צדקה,
im Gabbei Tzedakah, ולא בהקדש עם גזברים v'lo behekdesh im gizbarim
or not with the הקדש hekdesh funds that the treasurers of the...
with the treasurers of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. ואף על פי
שאין ראיה לדבר זכר לדבר, Ve'af al pi she'ein raya ledavar zecher
ledavar, although there is no evidence to this there's a hint to
this, שנאמר, shene'emar, ולא יחשבו את האנשים אשר יתנו את הכסף על
ידם לתת לעשי המלאכה, v'lo yechashvu et ha'anashim asher yitnu et hakesef
al yadam latet le'osei hamelacha, they would not you know do the
check the books, check the accounts, you know the specifics of those
that were given the authority to you know to distribute to do
the work of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, כי באמונה הם עשים,
ki ve'emuna hem osim, they have to act with faith and with
trust. ורש"י VehaRashi says why is that not a straight proof? So
רש"י Rashi says well they were supervised so many different activities it
would have been unreasonable to ask them to maintain records of everything.
תוספות Tosafot says more simply, ואף על פי שאין ראיה לדבר זכר
לדבר, ve'af al pi she'ein raya ledavar zecher ledavar, look at תוספות,
Tosafot, ראיה גמורה אינה דשאני התם שהיו צדיקים גמורים, raya gemura eina
deshani hatam shehayu tzaddikim gemurim, right maybe the point there is not
that anybody with this office is exempt from oversight maybe it was
just that was special about that case. It doesn't mean that we
would generally exempt people from that oversight. So again I really don't
know what to do with this גמרא Gemara because just our experience
shows so much against
that you know this idea. Anyway let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. Okay אמר רבי אלעזר, amar Rabbi Elazar, אף על פי
שיש לו לאדם גזבר נאמן בתוך
ביתו, af al pi sheyesh lo la'adam gizbar ne'eman betoch beito, even
if you have a trustworthy גזבר gizbar in your house or you
know somebody who's supervising
your you know your business activities and so on and you're not
supposed to
therefore check check the accounts afterwards or at least as we said
by צדקה, tzedakah. but nevertheless יצור וימנה yitzor veyimneh when you're giving
him the stuff to use the money you should bind it up
and count it out. So it's like a little weird like count
up the money make it very clear here it's a hundred dollars
one two three four five you count it even if they're not
going to check the accounts afterwards שנאמר
ויצרו וימנו shene'emar vayatzuru vayimnu they bound up the money and they
counted it so I don't somebody can explain to me afterwards why
it makes sense to do it at the front end and not
at the back end. אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, oh now
going back to that that's about trusting the גבאי gabbai צדקה tzedakah,
with a little diversion to this very fascinating issue about self-governance and
about sort of like you know groups of professional groups and so
on. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this אמר רב הונא,
amar Rav Huna, but now we're going back to how does one
distribute the money and determine whether somebody is deserving of the of
getting צדקה tzedakah because anybody can come and say you know stick
out their hand. Okay so אמר רב הונא, amar Rav Huna, בודקין
למזונות ואין בודקין לכסות, bodkin limezonot ve'ein bodkin licksut, you can check
somebody to make sure they're being they're honest and they really have
a need if they're asking for food but not if they're asking
for clothing. איבעית אימא קרא ואיבעית אימא סברא, Iba'it eima kra ve'iba'it
eima svara, I could argue this from a פסוק pasuk or from
logic. איבעית אימא סברא Iba'it eima svara from logic האי קמיבזי והאי
לא קמיבזי hai kamizvi vehai lo kamizvi a guy who needs clothing
who's in tatters every minute they're you know being embarrassed you know
that they're walking around you know half-clothed and the person who's hungry
they're feeling it on the inside but it's not something that is
embarrassing them in public it's not vis- it's not visible to others.
ואיבעית אימא קרא Ve'iba'it eima kra or you want you can point
out a פסוק. pasuk. הלא פרס לרעב לחמך, Halo faros lara'ev lachmecha,
spread out to the poor your bread בשין כתיב, beshin ketiv, so
even though it's פרס faros like לפרוס lifros to break a loaf
of bread it's written with a שין shin which is לפרוש lifrosh
to explicate or you know which means to sort of to investigate
to find out the specifics of the matter. So before you give
the poor your bread find out the specifics והדר הבא ליה vahadar
havlei and afterwards give. והתם כתיב Vehatam ketiv but when it comes
to clothing the poor it says כי תראה ערם וכסיתו ki tireh
arom vechisito as soon as you see the naked
person cover him clothe him. כי תראה לאלתר Ki tireh la'altar immediately
cover him. So that's one approach. ורב יהודה אמר, Verav Yehuda amar,
now רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says the reverse בודקין לכסות ואין בודקין
למזונות, bodkin licksut ve'ein bodkin limezonot, you can check into you know
whether somebody is really poor before you give them clothing but not
before you give them food. איבעית אימא סברא ואיבעית אימא קרא, Iba'it
eima svara ve'iba'it eima kra, I can tell this from logic or
from a פסוק. pasuk. איבעית אימא סברא Iba'it eima svara from סברא,
svara, האי קמיצטער והאי לא קמיצטער, hai kamitzta'ar vehai lo kamitzta'ar, the
opposite of the idea of נבזה. nivzeh. One guy it might be
more visible but the guy who's hungry is in pain is suffering
you know is suffering from hunger. איבעית אימא קרא Iba'it eima kra
and from a פסוק, pasuk, הכא כתיב, hacha ketiv, so we're going
to read the פסוק pasuk in a different way. הלא פרס לרעב
לחמך, Halo faros lara'ev lachmecha, break for the poor your bread פרס
לאלתר, paros la'altar, as soon immediately not with this דרשה drasha of
לפרוש. lifrosh. Okay וכקרינא ukecharina like the פסוק pasuk is read פרס
paros not פרוש. parosh. והתם כתיב Vehatam ketiv but by the clothing
it says כי תראה ערם וכסיתו, ki tireh arom vechisito, so the
verb follows you know here the before the verb פרס paros to
give the bread comes first the verb comes first here the verb
וכסיתו vechisito comes after you see the poor person comes at the
end. Okay וכשיראה לך vechasheyeira lecha when he proves to you when
he demonstrates to you that he really needs it then you provide
clothing. Also of course clothing will tend to be
By the way, the whole thing is fascinating because you read the
פסוקים psukim and the פסוקים psukim say, you know, when the עני
ani comes, it says פתוח תפתח את ידך לו, patoach tiftach et
yadecha lo, so you could say, who lets me investigate at all?
As soon as I don't give them immediately, maybe I'm transgressing, right?
So there's actually a חידוש chiddush here and I know we've all
experienced it, you know, people will come around asking for money or
whatever, do they really need money, right? So you know, you want
to give but you don't want to be taken advantage of or
whatever. So it's really fascinating that the rabbis say that you actually
have a right, at least in some cases, to investigate before, you
know, before you give. Okay?
Equalizing of סברא sevara and פסוק pasuk is interesting too.
Yeah, I mean that's been the constant theme, like we're quoting both.
Yeah. Okay.
There's a story of the person who waited to give to the
עני ani and by the time he said, well, let me get
to my home and then the עני ani died. Right, which particularly
in the case of food. Right. And you know, and like people
that also like I know people that are, you know, concerned, right,
about, well, you know, like, like, what are they going to use
the money for, do they really need it or whatever, but sometimes,
you know, but so some people use that as a way of
saying I don't give, but other people say, no, if I see
somebody on the street who's asking for something, like I'll walk them
into a store and I'll buy them some food, or I try
to carry with me some food at all times that I can
then offer to somebody, you know, so it's, you know, different ways
of sort of dealing with that. But yes, the height and the
obligation here particularly when somebody is hungry or says they're hungry and
needs food. Okay, תניא כוותיה דרבי יהודה, tanya kavatei de-Rabbi Yehuda, we
tell like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, אמר amar כסוני, kesuni, if somebody
says clothe me, בודקין אחריו, bodkin acharav, you first look into it.
פרנסוני, parnesuni, provide me food, אין בודקין, ein bodkin, you don't look
into it, you just provide them. Okay, תנן התם, tnan hatam, now
we're getting to again a different aspect here about the town providing
for the poor, and who do they provide for? Or what are
the, what are the ways they provide as a collective, as a
town? אין פוחתין לעני העובר ממקום למקום מככר בפונדיון מארבע סאין בסלע.
ein pochtin le-ani ha-over mi-makom le-makom mi-kikar be-pundiyon me-arba se'in be-sela. You
do not give less to a poor person passing through, and remember
that's the person that eats from the soup kitchen, you don't give
less than a loaf of bread that cost a פונדיון pundiyon which
is a small coin when four סאה se'ah of wheat are going
for a סלע. sela. I'm not going to figure the whole thing
out for you, but a certain loaf of bread, okay, fine. לן,
lan, once he sleeps over in the city, that's when he's just
passing through, if he sleeps in the city, נותנין לו פרנסת לינה,
notnin lo parnasat lina, you have to provide him the wherewithal to
sleep, you know, the accommodations of sleeping. מאי פרנסת לינה? mai parnasat
lina? What does that mean? אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Pappa, פוריא,
purya, a bed, וביסדיא, u-visadya, and a pillow. So it's really fascinating,
right? You got a soup kitchen, you have a what's it called?
Shelter, right, a shelter for people providing them a place to sleep.
Okay.
Now, שבת, Shabbat, if he stays for שבת, Shabbat, נותנין לו מזון
שלוש סעודות, notnin lo mazon shalosh se'udot, you provide him three meals
to carry him over for שבת. Shabbat. תוספות, Tosafot, there's a whole
discussion when do you provide him the meals or whatever, I'm not
going to get into that. Okay. תנא, tana, this is just a
poor person, right? So even though the poor person, and this is
just a passing through, so even though, you know, you might not
be have to give him like from the קופה, kuppah, you still
are giving him on a daily basis, but you have to give
him the extra food for שבת, Shabbat, he's also gets שלוש סעודות
shalosh se'udot for שבת. Shabbat. Right? He should not have to do
a lesser שבת Shabbat than anybody else. Now there's an important תוספות,
Tosafot, because תוספות Tosafot asks the question that there's a גמרא Gemara
where רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says better that a person should make
שבת Shabbat like a weekday, meaning not spend any extra money on
extra food for שבת Shabbat or whatever, rather than have to accept
צדקה tzedakah from other people. So תוספות Tosafot says what, here it
sounds like you give them צדקה tzedakah for
שלוש סעודות. shalosh se'udot.
Why not? It depends on you or on them.
Exactly. So look at the bottom of תוספות Tosafot שבת, Shabbat, the
last like last wide line where it says like four lines before
the lines get wide in תוספות, Tosafot, he says וניראה לרשב"א, ve-nir'eh
le-Rashba, that's not the רשב"א Rashba of the, whatever, the Sephardi רשב"א.
Rashba. Anyway, דבשביל סעודת שבת אין לו להלוות וליטול, de-bishvil se'udat Shabbat
ein lo le-halvot ve-litol, if you haven't borrowed money to begin with,
then don't go ahead and borrow money for, not even take צדקה,
tzedakah, you shouldn't even like put yourself in a dependent relationship with
other people. Don't even borrow money to provide שלוש סעודות. shalosh se'udot.
Better that you should not have to need that, you know, be
in that relationship and that dependency relationship. אבל בשכבר צריך ליטול, aval
be-she-kevar tzarich litol, once you've already been accepting money from other people,
whether by a loan or a gift, נוטל גם כדי סעודת שבת,
notel gam kedei se'udat Shabbat, then you should take, even they have
to give you and you should be taking even to provide for
yourself for שבת. Shabbat. Okay.
Any שבת Shabbat meal or three?
No, any שבת Shabbat meal, שלוש סעודות shalosh se'udot for שבת. Shabbat.
So you should... you should rather not have any food on שבת?
Shabbat?
Oh, well the language is עשה שבתך חול, aseh Shabat-cha chol, don't
go spend any extra for שבת, Shabbat, right? If you can't put
food on the table, whether שבת Shabbat or the weekday, I mean
if you've been going hungry throughout the week and been living on
like you know a loaf of, you know, whatever, a few crumbs
a day, then the same thing on שבת, Shabbat, you know.
He's talking about looking older and doing things during the week and...
Right, right. Okay, can't go into the whole thing. Let's go on.
Right, that's your own money, exactly. Okay. Alright. Okay, now תנא tana
back to the גמרא. Gemara. We're taught in a ברייתא: brayta: אם
היה מחזיר על הפתחים אין נזקקין לו. Im haya machzir al haptachim
ein nizkakim lo. Now this is fascinating, right, this whole issue about
like, oh, you know, like when you provide people welfare does it
create a disincentive for them to work because then they go to
work and then they lose their welfare. So here the question is,
if you have a poor person who's not exactly, you know, working
as we would say, but he's raising his own money, he's going
door-to-door, knocking on the doors, he's playing his guitar in the subway,
he's getting his own funds, okay, then you don't have to give
him from the communal funds. He's taken care of himself. All right,
which is interesting. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this,
where are we? אין נזקקין לו. ein nizkakim lo. ההוא עניא, hahu
anya, a certain poor person, דהוה מחזיר על
הפתחים, d'hava machzir al haptachim, was going door-to-door, דאתא לקמיה דרב פפא,
d'ata l'kamei d'Rav Pappa, came to רב פפא, Rav Pappa, who was
in charge of providing communal funds, ולא איזדקק ליה, v'lo izdakak leh,
and רב פפא Rav Pappa didn't give him anything from the communal
funds. אמר ליה רב סמא בריה דרב ייבא לרב פפא, amar leh
Rav Sama brei d'Rav Yeiva l'Rav Pappa, רב סמא Rav Sama said
to רב פפא: Rav Pappa: אי מר לא מזדקק ליה, ei mar
lo mizdakak leh, if the master is not going to give, if
people see you don't give him any צדקה tzedakah and you're over
all the communal funds, אינשי אחריני לא מזדקקו ליה, inshi achrinei lo
mizdakku leh, nobody else will give him. Okay, if he's going to
go door-to-door and everyone's going to say, why should I give you,
I saw even רב פפא Rav Pappa wouldn't give you any money
from our צדקה tzedakah funds. So לימות ברעב, leimus b'ra'av, should he
die?
So the גמרא Gemara says, והתניא, v'hatanya, but what do you mean,
the ברייתא brayta says אם היה עני מחזיר על הפתחים אין נזקקין
לו, im haya any machzir al haptachim ein nizkakim lo, if he's
going door-to-door, we don't give him from the communal funds. So אמר
ליה, amar leh, he said to him, אין נזקקין לו למתנה מרובה,
ein nizkakim lo l'matanah merubah, you don't give him the full amount,
okay, אבל נזקקין לו למתנה מועטת, aval nizkakim lo l'matanah muetet, you
give him a small amount, maybe a nominal amount, but people need
to see that, you know, you're sending a very bad message if
you turn him away. Okay, it's, so yes, so give him something,
at least something nominal. אמר רב אסי, amar Rav Assi, said רב
אסי, Rav Assi, לעולם אל ימנע אדם את עצמו מלתת שלישית השקל
בשנה. l'olam al yimna adam et atzmo miletet shlishit hashekel b'shanah. Okay,
a person should not, even if, you know, obviously you have these
communal responsibilities, you're supposed to give somebody who comes up to you,
but let's say you're in a place where nobody comes up to
you to ask you for money, it's a town that doesn't have
poor people going through it, whatever it is, nevertheless you have to
make sure that minimally in a year you give a third of
a שקל, shekel, שנאמר, she'ne'emar, which is interesting, what ever happened to
the idea of מעשר כספים? ma'aser kesafim? So מעשר כספים ma'aser kesafim
is not so much in the גמרא. Gemara. מעשר כספים ma'aser kesafim
is more in the ראשונים, Rishonim, it's in some מדרש הלכה, Midrash
Halacha, it's a separate discussion. But the גמרא Gemara here speaks about
a bare minimum, if for some reason all the other collections are
not being made of you, then a bare minimum of a third
of a שקל. shekel. שנאמר והעמדנו עלינו מצות לתת עלינו שלישית השקל
בשנה לעבודת בית אלוקינו. She'ne'emar v'he'emadnu aleinu mitzvot latet aleinu shlishit hashekel
b'shanah l'avodat beit Elokeinu. Which is interesting, we put upon ourselves obligations,
מצות, mitzvot, to give a third of a שקל shekel a year
to the building of, you know, the house of our Lord. ואמר
רב
אסי, v'amar Rav Assi, שקולה צדקה כנגד כל מצות, shkulah tzedakah k'neged
kol mitzvot, צדקה tzedakah is equivalent to all of the מצות, mitzvot,
שנאמר והעמדנו עלינו מצות. she'ne'emar v'he'emadnu aleinu mitzvot. We said we put
on ourselves מצות, mitzvot, מצוה mitzvah אין כתיב כאן אלא מצות. ein
ktiv kan ela mitzvot. So giving of צדקה tzedakah is like the
total of... Of course it doesn't exactly... צדקה tzedakah that was more
for temple funds, right? You look at תוספות, Tosafot, והעמדנו עלינו מצות
ואע"ג דהאי קרא גבי בית אלוקינו כתיב דהיינו בדק הבית, v'he'emadnu aleinu
mitzvot v'af al gav d'hai kra gabei beit Elokeinu ktiv d'hainu bedek
habayit, the building of the temple, כל שכן לצדקה. kol sheken l'tzedakah.
That's very nice. You could have said, no, only the building of
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, so what are you talking about? צדקה
tzedakah is more important, צדקה tzedakah has real people that are suffering,
right? So that's a very powerful two words of תוספות, Tosafot, quite
powerful, right? How much is, you know, and it's an interesting question
how people use their own צדקה tzedakah funds, right? Do people, a
lot of people probably think, I want to give something that's more
obviously religious like giving to I don't know, a שול shul thing
or whatever than to actually providing for poor people. Okay, so I
mean, a lot of people don't think that way, but clearly it's
really a helpful, you know, corrective, this type of a תוספות Tosafot
for the way some people think. Okay, כל שכן לצדקה. kol sheken
l'tzedakah. Okay, back to the גמרא, Gemara, of course we didn't catch
up, but let's at least turn the
page. Okay, אמר אלעזר, amar Elazar, אמר רבי אלעזר, amar Rabbi Elazar,
גדול המעשה, gadol hama'aseh, this is a big line that's quoted a
little bit suggested earlier, יותר מן העושה. yoter min ha'oseh. The one
that gets people to give has more reward than the people that
give, presumably because he's getting many people to give, right, that's the
word מצדיקי הרבים, matzdikei harabbim, the ones that cause the רבים rabbim
to give צדקה. tzedakah. שנאמר והיה מעשה הצדקה שלום ועבודת הצדקה השקט
ובטח עד עולם. She'ne'emar v'haya ma'aseh hatzedakah shalom va'avodat hatzedakah hashket vavetach
ad olam. So מעשה הצדקה, ma'aseh hatzedakah, the one who does the
צדקה, tzedakah, meaning who gets others, who makes others do the צדקה,
tzedakah, he has, you know, he has שלום, shalom, and the one
who, you know, and presumably the one who just does, gives the
צדקה tzedakah himself is השקט ובטח, hashket vavetach, which presumably is not
as great as שלום. shalom. Okay, זכה, zacha, now if the person
merits, הלא פרוס לרעב לחמך, halo feros lara'av lachmecha, you give צדקה,
tzedakah, you merit, it goes to the poor. לא זכה, lo zacha,
if you don't merit, ועניים מרודים תביא בית, v'aniyim merudim tavi bayit,
you bring the downtrodden into the house. What's the problem with that?
So רש"י Rashi says the word מרודים merudim here means those who
complain, and what it really is referring to is the Roman government,
that if you do not provide for your own poor, then the
government is... get involved in collecting money from you to provide for
the poor and you'd much rather do it yourselves than get the
government involved. Okay. אמר להו רבא, amar lehu Rava, so let's just
read that, לבני מחוזא livnei Mechuza to the people of מחוזא, Mechuza,
במטותא מינייכו, bematuta minaychu, do me a favor guys, עוסו בהדי הדדי,
usu bahadei hadadei, get take care of one another כי היכי דלהוי
לכו שלמא דמלכותא, ki heichi delahavei lachon shalma demalchuta, so there should
be peace with you and the government so you don't get the
government upset that you're not providing for one another and then the
government has to get involved in all of your dealings. ואמר רבי
אלעזר, ve'amar Rabbi Elazar, בזמן שבית המקדש קיים, bizman shebeit hamikdash kayam,
when the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash was around, אדם שוקל שקלו ומתכפר
לו, adam shokel shiklo umitkapeir lo, you gave your שקל shekel for
the communal sacrifices and then you were atoned for. עכשיו שאין בית
המקדש קיים, achshav she'ein beit hamikdash kayam, אם עושים צדקה מוטב, im
osim tzedakah mutav, if you do צדקה tzedakah it's good, ואם לאו
באים עובדי כוכבים ונוטלים בזרוע, ve'im lav ba'im ovdei kochavim venotlim bizroa,
and if you don't then the government will come and they'll force
you to give the money. ואף על פי כן נחשב להם לצדקה,
ve'af al pi chein nechshav lahem letzedakah, sorry guys just let me
finish this sentence, even though they force you to give, you should
know that you'll still get credit for giving צדקה, tzedakah, שנאמר shenemar
ונוגשייך צדקה, venogshayich tzedakah, okay, those who force you in right צדקה,
tzedakah, it's a hard פסוק pasuk to do, but here we bring,
those who force you to give, it'll still be צדקה. tzedakah. So
very interesting, take care of your own needs and also the comparison
of צדקה tzedakah to aspects of building the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
bringing קרבנות, korbanot, all to be considered as well.
Okay. Good morning. Good morning.
Good morning.